{"tossups": [{"question": "MRN recruits ataxia telangi\u00c2\u00b7ectasia mutated during this process to facilitate gamma H2AX production. Lig-4 complexes with XRCC4 during a form of this process. 53BP1 is countered by the activity of BRCA1 when this process is performed during S or G2 phase. A protein kinase complex used for this general process is also needed for telomere stability and B and T cell maturation and is localized to specific sites by its Ku70 and Ku80 proteins. A defect in a type of this process causes xeroderma pigmentosum. Pathways in this process include nonhomologous end-joining, which addresses double-strand breaks such as those caused by ionizing radiation. For 10 points, name this process in which lesions on a namesake genetic molecule are patched.", "answer": "DNA repair [or nucleotide excision repair; or NER; or base excision repair; or BER; or mismatch repair; or homology-directed repair; or HDR; or nonhomologous end-joining or NHEJ until \"nonhomologous\" is read; prompt on homologous recombination; prompt on partial answers]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>DNA repair</u></b> [or <b><u>nucleotide excision repair</u></b>; or <b><u>NER</u></b>; or <b><u>base excision repair</u></b>; or <b><u>BER</u></b>; or <b><u>mismatch repair</u></b>; or <b><u>homology-directed repair</u></b>; or <b><u>HDR</u></b>; or <b><u>nonhomologous end-joining</u></b> or <b><u>NHEJ until \"nonhomologous\" is read</u></b>; prompt on <u>homologous recombination</u>; prompt on <u>partial answers</u>]", "acceptable": ["DNA repair", "nucleotide excision repair", "NER", "base excision repair", "BER", "mismatch repair", "homology-directed repair", "HDR", "nonhomologous end-joining", "NHEJ until \"nonhomologous\" is read"], "promptable": ["homologous recombination", "partial answers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One character in this novel intentionally overeats to gain weight because his wife hurts him every time he tries to beat her. Another character in this novel scars his face to match that of the girl he wants to marry, a member of an African tribe that worships roofleaves, the Olinka. This novel's protagonist starts a business making pants after moving to Tennessee with a singer known as the Queen Honeybee. A woman in this novel is sentenced to twelve years in jail for attacking the mayor after his wife asks her to be their maid. In this novel, the protagonist discovers her husband has been hiding letters from her sister Nettie, which are recovered with help from Shug Avery. For 10 points, name this epistolary novel in which Celie addresses many letters to God, a work of Alice Walker.", "answer": "The Color Purple", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Color Purple</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Color Purple"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The base of a statue of one of these people includes a globe inscribed with the zodiacal signs of Taurus, Capricorn, and Scorpio. A wreath of oak leaves is held above one of these people in the upper tier of a dual-level gemma carved from Arabian onyx. A small Cupid rides on a dolphin at the feet of one of these people in a sculpture featuring an intricately-rendered breastplate. Michelangelo made the centerpiece of his design for the Capitoline Piazza a 175 AD bronze sculpture of one of these men that served as a prototype for Renaissance equestrian statues. The first of these rulers commissioned a monument to peace called the Ara Pacis. For 10 points, name these rulers depicted in portrait sculptures such as the Augustus of Primaporta.", "answer": "Roman emperors [or emperor of Rome; or Imperator; or Princeps; or Caesar; or Augustus until it is read; prompt on emperors; prompt on Roman rulers] ", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Roman emperors</u></b> [or <b><u>emperor of Rome</u></b>; or <b><u>Imperator</u></b>; or <b><u>Princeps</u></b>; or <b><u>Caesar</u></b>; or <b><u>Augustus until it is read</u></b>; prompt on <u>emperors</u>; prompt on <u>Roman rulers</u>]", "acceptable": ["Roman emperors", "emperor of Rome", "Imperator", "Princeps", "Caesar", "Augustus until it is read"], "promptable": ["emperors", "Roman rulers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man challenged Henry Frank to a debate conducted in Yiddish after Frank accused this man of antisemitism. When newspaper deliverymen in his city went on strike, this man read the Sunday Dick Tracy comics out loud on the radio show Talk to the People. A namesake committee established by this man found that smoking marijuana \"does not lead to addiction in the medical sense of the word\". After he gave a radio address promising to \"drive the bums out of town\", this man started a campaign to find and destroy slot machines owned by Frank Costello. Along with George Norris, this man co-sponsored a bill that banned employers from forcing workers to sign yellow-dog contracts. For 10 points, name this Italian-American mayor of New York who names a New York City airport.", "answer": "Fiorello LaGuardia ", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Fiorello LaGuardia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Fiorello LaGuardia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Luke Timothy Johnson argues for an early dating for this book since it makes no reference to events in Jesus's life, suggesting lack of access to the Gospels. In one section, this work counters early Christian antinomianism by arguing that the Binding of Isaac story demonstrates the necessity of circumcision and obedience. This book is cited as the inspiration for the Christian practice of anointing the sick, and it claims that it is \"pure joy\" to \"face trials of many kinds\". Martin Luther called this document an \"epistle of straw\" because of its claim that \"faith without works is dead\". This book's author shares his name with an apostle who is the patron saint of Spain. For 10 points, name this non- Pauline epistle whose author is traditionally identified with Jesus's brother, called \"the Just\".", "answer": "Epistle of James", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Epistle of James</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Epistle of James"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A character in this series is poisoned alongside her husband by her former lover, a Brazilian baron, after marrying a perfumer for his money. In a work of this series, a sculptor falls in love with an actress only to find out that she is a castrato, sending the sculptor into a murderous rage after Zambinella. In another work in this series, a Polish sculptor named Wenceslas Steinbock marries Hortense Hulot (or- TONSE yoo-LOW). The title object of a work in this series grows smaller every time that it grants a wish to Raphael de Valentin (vah-lon-TAN), and a story in it was analyzed by Roland Barthes in S/Z. The criminal Vautrin (voh-TRAN) and the ambitious Rastignac (ross-teen-YOCK) are characters in this series, which includes \"Sarrasine\", The Wild Ass's Skin, and Cousin Bette. For 10 points, name this sprawling series of novels by Honore\u0301 de Balzac.", "answer": "The Human Comedy [or La Come\u0301die humaine]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Human Comedy</u></b> [or <b><u>La Come\u0301die humaine</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["The Human Comedy", "La Come\u0301die humaine"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Prior to this country's 2015 presidential election, the ruling party appointed nine hundred thousand mandataires to oversee the vote. In the documentary Fatal Assistance, its president claimed he would have been overthrown had he not allowed the rival INITE party on the ballot. A group of opposition leaders in this country called the G-8 have demanded new elections. Jovenel Moise recently won its first round of presidential voting. Banana Man and Sweet Micky are nicknames of politicians from this country. In June 2015, ProPublica found that the American Red Cross had collected five hundred million dollars but built only six houses in this country following a disaster. For 10 points, name this Caribbean country, still recovering from a 2010 earthquake.", "answer": "Haiti", "category": "Current Events", "subcategory": "Current Events", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Haiti</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Haiti"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The fortieth verse of the \"Parties\" sura may be an interpolation regarding the status of these people. A hadith analogizes a person's relationship to this role as the brick which forms the corner of a house, and two others claim that there will be either twenty-three men and four women, or thirty total individuals, who spuriously claim to be this type of person in the future. The major heresies of the Ahmadiyyas and Baha\u0301'i\u0301, respectively, were claiming that Mirza Ghulam Ahmad and Baha\u0301'u'lla\u0301h were this kind of person. The belief that Muhammad was the \"Khatam\" of these people is commonly expressed by analogy to a wax seal. For 10 points, name these people in Islam who bring the message of God.", "answer": "prophets", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>prophets</u></b>", "acceptable": ["prophets"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "For a map f between a compact manifold M and connected manifold N, this quantity modulo two is defined as the order of the preimage of a regular value modulo two. For a homogeneous function f, Euler showed that the sum, over i, of x-sub-i times the partial of f with respect to x-sub-i, is equal to this quantity times f. This word is used to denote the dimension of a field extension as a vector space over its base field. Abel, Ruffini, and Galois (gal-WAH) independently showed that there is no general algebraic formula for the roots of certain functions that have a value of this quantity that is larger than five. Depending on convention, this value is either equal to negative infinity or zero for the zero polynomial. For 10 points, what word describes the largest exponent of a polynomial's terms?", "answer": "degree [or deg; or order]", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>degree</u></b> [or <b><u>deg</u></b>; or <b><u>order</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["degree", "deg", "order"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This company employed the doctor Morris Young to establish two hospitals to protect its workers from disease. Workers of this company were housed in a slum derisively nicknamed the Paper City. During World War II, the products of this company, along with those of its competitors, were mixed and sold as \"pool\". The expeditions of George Reynolds were authorized by the Green Document obtained by its founder, William D'Arcy. The overthrow of Mohammad Mossadegh revitalized this company, which had operated a massive refinery at Abadan. This company was leasing the Deepwater Horizon rig when an explosion in 2009 caused the largest oil spill of all time. For 10 points, name this company once called the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and often known by a two-letter acronym.", "answer": "BP [or British Petroleum; or AIO or Anglo-Iranian Oil Company until it is read]", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>BP</u></b> [or <b><u>British Petroleum</u></b>; or <b><u>AIO</u></b> or <b><u>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company until it is read</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["BP", "British Petroleum", "AIO", "Anglo-Iranian Oil Company until it is read"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A four-dimensional form of this quantity is defined as the zero-th basis vector of an MCRF. A simpler form of a composition law for this quantity results when setting this quantity equal to the hyperbolic tangent of a namesake parameter, due to the angle addition formula for the hyperbolic tangent. A form of this quantity is the reciprocal of the slope of a world line. A non-intuitive result for this quantity is that it must be added using Einstein's law of addition. Newton's laws are all Galilean invariant, meaning that they are the same when a constant factor of this quantity is applied. It appears divided by the square of the speed of light in the Lorentz factor. Because the proper time along a null line is zero, the four-dimensional form of this quantity cannot be used to define a photon's four- momentum. For 10 points, identify this quantity whose time derivative is acceleration.", "answer": "relative velocity [or v]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>relative velocity</u></b> [or <b><u>v</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["relative velocity", "v"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In The Light of Common Day, Diana Duff-Cooper recalls finding her food ill-tasting because this man was so bad at dinner conversation. He gained the nickname \"The Bloody Baron\" for suppressing communist movements, becoming the only person to have fought against Germany to receive the Iron Cross. This man ordered the construction of six POW camps called Keskitysleiri (KESS-kee-toos-LAY-ree). Thor Damen recorded several minutes of a private conversation between this man and Hitler when Hitler visited him for his seventy-fifth birthday. He served eight years as chairman of his country's defence council, and he was promoted to field marshal by the time of the Continuation War. For 10 points, name this Finnish statesman who established a namesake defensive line across the Karelian isthmus.", "answer": "Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a Madonna lactans by this artist, mountains can be seen through two arched windows, and Christ holds a goldfinch. Christ escapes the embrace of his mother, whose spinning tool resembles a miniature cross, in the Buccleuch and Lansdowne Madonnas by this artist, collectively known as the Madonna of the Yarnwinder. Two side panels depicting musician angels were part of an altarpiece containing this artist's best-known Madonna, which exists in two versions at the Louvre and National Gallery in London, both of which feature an angel and John the Baptist alongside Mary and Jesus in a craggy landscape. For 10 points, name this artist whose commissions for Ludovico Sforza in Milan include The Virgin of the Rocks and The Last Supper.", "answer": "Leonardo da Vinci [or Leonardo di ser Piero da Vinci]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "Leonardo da <b><u>Vinci</u></b> [or <b><u>Leonardo di ser Piero da Vinci</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Leonardo da Vinci", "Leonardo di ser Piero da Vinci"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The last verse paragraph of a longer poem by this author begins, \"The world stands out on either side, no wider than the heart is wide\". In a poem by this writer, a mother who sings while making a pair of mittens and a little blouse tells her son, \"you've need of clothes to cover you, and not a rag have I\". The speaker of another poem by this writer sees \"three islands in a bay\" and traces \"the line of the horizon\". This poet of \"The Ballad of the Harp-Weaver\" wrote a poem at the age of 19 that begins, \"All I could see from where I stood was three long mountains and a wood\". In a short poem by her, the speaker says, \"My candle burns at both ends, it will not last the night\". For 10 points, name this American poet who wrote \"Renascence\" and \"First Fig\".", "answer": "Edna St. Vincent Millay", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Edna St. Vincent <b><u>Millay</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Edna St. Vincent Millay"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A ten-minute-long piece in this genre comprises a slow movement marked \"Ruhig schreitend\" (ROO- eek SHRYE-tint) and a fast theme-and-variations movement. That Anton Webern (VAY-burn) piece in this genre is scored for nine instruments. It is not a violin sonata, but three movements exhibiting cyclic form comprise a D minor piece in this genre by Ce\u0301sar Franck (fronk). In a programmatic piece in this genre, near the end of the fourth movement, a wistful clarinet solo plays just before a loud tutti chord depicting a guillotine. In that piece in this genre, depictions of \"Re\u0302veries \u00c2\u2013 Passions\", a \"March to the Scaffold\", and a \"Dream of a Witches' Sabbath\" all distort the central \"ide\u0301e fixe\" (ee-DAY FEEKS). For 10 points, name this genre in which Hector Berlioz wrote a piece titled fantastique.", "answer": "symphony", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>symphony</u></b>", "acceptable": ["symphony"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "W. Arthur Lewis's model of developing economies is named after this number. The New York game has this many equilibriums. It is the number of fundamental theorems of welfare economics. This is the highest payoff available in the standard formulation of the Battle of the Sexes game, which, like the Stag Hunt game, has this many equilibriums. An alternate name for the Heckscher\u00c2\u2013Ohlin model is based on this number, because it was originally formulated using this many products and this many countries. Each player in the prisoner's dilemma has this many possible actions, and it is also the number of players in the game. For 10 points, name this number of axes in the standard graphic representation of supply and demand.", "answer": "two", "category": "Social Science", "subcategory": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>two</u></b>", "acceptable": ["two"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Worshipers of this god beat statues of him after unsuccessful hunts, and remained quiet during mid-day to avoid disturbing his naps. Plutarch's \"On the Failure of Oracles\" describes how a voice informed the sailor Thamus of the death of this \"great god\". Zeus fell in love with Io thanks to a charm cast by this god's daughter Iynx, whom he fathered with Echo. This god helped retrieve Zeus's sinews by shouting to frighten the dragon Delphyne. King Midas got his donkey ears by claiming that this god had won a contest against Apollo. This god pursued the nymph Syrinx to the River Ladon, where she transformed into the reeds which he used to make his trademark instrument. For 10 points, name this goat-legged, pipe-playing Greek god of nature.", "answer": "Pan", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pan</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Pan"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A monarch of this house urged his foreign subjects to accept British rule in the Kew Letters and faced a revolt led by the Patriots faction. Gaspar Fagel authored several open letters in the name of a member of this house. Following the Treaty of Arras, a bounty of 25,000 crowns was put on a member of this house, motivating his assassination by Balthasar Gerard. A member of this house, whose powers were limited in the Act of Seclusion, landed at Brixham after receiving a letter from the Immortal Seven. The Eighty Years' War was partially incited by a member of this house known as \"the Silent\", and a later member of this house took the British throne via the Glorious Revolution. For 10 points, name this colorfully-named house of many Dutch people called William.", "answer": "House of Orange-Nassau ", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>House of Orange-Nassau</u></b>", "acceptable": ["House of Orange-Nassau"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Some astronomical observatories use laser guide stars to excite this element in the atmosphere because that creates a wavefront reference for adaptive optics. An experimental type of nuclear reactor cooled by this element, sometimes in an alloy with potassium, includes the extremely accident-plagued Monju Nuclear Power Plant. Pretty much all of the solid form of this element used commercially is prepared using a mixture of it and calcium chloride in a Downs cell. The solvent for aluminum oxide in the Hall\u00c2\u2013He\u0301roult (ay-ROO) process is a mixture of aluminum and this element bound to fluoride; that mixture is cryolite. A 588.99 and 589.59 nanometer doublet in an astronomical object's spectrum corresponds to this element's D lines. For 10 points, name this element that forms a molten salt above 801 degrees Celsius when bound to chlorine.", "answer": "sodium [or Na] ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>sodium</u></b> [or <b><u>Na</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["sodium", "Na"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The protagonist of this story is forced to be a witness for a wedding because he is the only man in a church. A character in this story who first appears wearing a mask introduces himself as the Count Von Kramm. Early in this story, two men are able to surmise that a piece of paper originated in mainland Europe because of the markings of its manufacturer. Its central scheme involves throwing a plumber's rocket into the residence of a woman who will be forced to reveal the location of her most prized possession because she thinks that the building is on fire. This story's plot is sent into motion when a European duke asks its central characters to retrieve a damaging photograph from Irene Adler. For 10 points, name this Sherlock Holmes story named after a Czech region.", "answer": "\"A Scandal in Bohemia\"", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>\"A Scandal in Bohemia\"</u></b>", "acceptable": ["\"A Scandal in Bohemia\""], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Most phase diagrams of this type switch between solid solution and intermetallic, with distinct liquidus and solidus lines. An application of the conservation of mass to this type of phase diagram results in the lever rule, which involves computing the relative lengths of tie lines. A peritectoid reaction involving this many phases yields one new phase. For this type of system, the Gibbs phase rule is simplified to degrees of freedom equals four minus number of phases. A very important and complex example of this type of phase diagram is the iron\u00c2\u2013carbon one because iron and carbon are the constituents of steel. For 10 points, name this type of phase diagram that features only two components.", "answer": "binary phase diagram [or binary alloy; or two component systems; prompt on alloys or multicomponent systems] ", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>binary phase diagram</u></b> [or <b><u>binary alloy</u></b>; or <b><u>two component systems</u></b>; prompt on <u>alloys</u> or <u>multicomponent systems</u>]", "acceptable": ["binary phase diagram", "binary alloy", "two component systems"], "promptable": ["alloys", "multicomponent systems"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}